hello friends welcome to dotnet awesome
dot-com in one of my previous article I
have shown you how to implement custom
forms authentication in a spirited MVC
for application today I am going to show
you how to secure a spirited web api
using token-based authentication yes we
don't need web appear is a framework
that makes it easy to build HTTP
services that reach a broad range of
clients including browsers mobile
devices and traditional desktop
application now it is Web API adoption
is increasing at a rapid pace so it is
very essential to implement security for
all type of client application trying to
access data from Web API services
nowadays the most preferred approach to
secure server resources by
authenticating users in web api is to
use sign token which contains enough
data to identify a particular user this
is called token based approach token
based approach is the most paper'd as
because of this following reason it's
loosely coupling the client application
is not tied to a particular
authentication schema the token is
generated validated and ferb perform the
authentication by the server second is
mobile friendly in native platform like
iOS Android Windows 8 etc handling
cookies are not an easy task token based
approach simplifies this a lot now the
question is how token-based
authentication actually works in the
token based approach client application
first send a request to authentication
server endpoint
with appropriate credentials now if the
username and password is found correct
then the authentication server send a
token to
as a response this token contains enough
data to identify a particular user and
an expiry time the client application
then use the token to access the
restricted resources in next requests
till the token is valid
okay let's start implementing
token-based authentication in Web API
first of all we will create an empty
project so first please open your visual
studio Here I am using Visual Studio
2013 okay fork it and project go to file
menu then click new and then click on
project you can see your a dialog window
appear from here I will select a speed
or need web application under wave then
you enter your application name
then select your project location is it
okay and then click on OK button it will
brings up a new dialog window for select
template here I will select empty
template so select empty template and
then I will add MVC and wave API Co
references so I check this too and then
click on OK button our application is
created you can see here in the solution
Explorer our application is created now
for implement token-based authentication
in wave api we need to install some
resources from nougat packages into our
application and so go to your reference
folder from solution Explorer
right-click on the references manage
nougat packages from here I'll search
for
Oh in I will install this one Microsoft
dot weighing dot host dot system wave so
I need this one
can see here the require dependencies is
also installed with this you can see
here the wean system wave and Microsoft
dot win Stein and it installed this also
Microsoft dot Wayne dots equity dot over
so click on install button it will also
install required dependences for this
you can see here this is install Mike
sub dot Wayne dot security and one more
thing I need to install this one this is
required for cross-origin resource
sharing
it's done
so all the required resources we have
installed in our project now we will add
a class in our application for validate
the credential for users and generate
token for adding the class go to your
solution Explorer right click on your
application aim then go to add and then
click new item from here I'll select
class enter your class name my
authorization provider and then click on
Add button so you can see here our class
is created my class name is my
authorization server provider here I
will innate one class ortho
authorization server provider
in this class I will override to method
from ortho authorization server provider
class one is validate client
authentication and second one is grant
resource owner brilliant CL so public
overwrite all right validate client
authentication I don't need this one
changes to sync and here our to one
single large context dot validated this
single line means that I have validated
the client you can see here I have
override validate client authentication
method from Earth authorization server
provider this method is used for valued
client application for the sake of
simplicity we will deep dive on validate
client authentication method later I
have just written one line here now is
context dot valuated this line is mean
means I evaluated the client so the
second method is grant resource owner
credential we will override so public
override grant resource on cadencia this
one this I'll make it awesome okay
in this method we will validate the
credential of users and if we found
valid currency L we will generate the
sign token using which user can access
authorized resources of server first of
all I will declare a variable identity
sequel to names identity
context
authentication type
and then we will valuate the client KHL
here
so if context dot username equals to
admin and context password to Adam
if it is then I will add some claims
identity dot add plane
dives
we can add in this way as well one more
I will add for showing the full name M
times dot name
so if username and password is admin
admin then this will happen one more I
will create for now what aced context
Con Ed start first with testicles to
using I will do the same thing I am
doing this just for showing you at the
testing time everything is perfect
otherwise I will return error so sit
later
and to add this one sorry
context dot validated identity I have to
add this line to here also you can see
here for now
I am using static data for validate user
here for make the application simple
later part of this series I will
validate user from database when we will
implement client application in angular
JS for token-based authentication this
is done now
now we will add you in start-up class
where we will configure the author
authorization server for adding wing
start up class go to your solution
Explorer right click on your project
name go to add then add item from you
here search for Wien start up + select
this one I'll renew it start up dot CS
and then click on Add button
our wind startup class is created now we
will configure author authorization
server here first of all I will enable
cross origin for enabling cross origin
request I need to add this line app dot
use cross
use Microsoft dot dot
ah start corruption start Allah all so
this line is for enabling cross-origin
requests
now we will configure the ortho
authorization server here first of all I
will get a reference of my provider to
knew my relation server provider this
one and then then we will define
authorization server options so
authorization to write radiation server
options as this is a demo project so I
need to allow and secure HTTP
in the live version we should make it
HTTP form HTTP version for secured now
the token endpoint path give this token
sorry it should new stream this is the
path from where user will get the token
after providing the valid credential now
I need to access token expiry turn span
to provide the time free owed the access
token remains valid after it was
generated so it's from
from days one I make it for one day
valid after generate to define the fovea
my provider
or to authorization server options then
I need to tell the application to use
ortho authorization server and this one
one more line we need to add when you
add token
options
and finally we need to register wave API
config HTTP
pick dot mister config so this is done
now we need to add a class for override
authorized attribute when building an
HTTP REST API you should use appropriate
HTTP response codes to indicate the
status of a response I always use 4 0 1
& 4 0 3 status code forget
authentication and authorization status
for 0 1 means unauthenticated it's
indicates that the request has not been
applied because it lacks valid
authentication credential for the target
resource and 4 0 3 for Vidan when the
user is authenticated but it's not
authorized to perform the requested
operation on the given response we
should use 4 0 3 to identify that
request is forbidden unfortunately the
wave api MVC web api authorized
attribute does not behave that way it
always emits 4 0 1 in both case for
authenticate author user or authorized
user so here in our wave API application
I am going to add a class for override
this behavior where we will return 4 0 3
when the user is authenticated but not
authorized to perform the requested
operation for adding the class just go
to your solution Explorer right click on
your project name then go add and you
can choose class from here also or from
here also add new item
so here I will rename it is active
and then click on Add button so it's
added now I will inherit authorized
attribute system dot dot wave dot t--
t-- p dot authorize attribute here i
will overwrite handle unauthorized
request so public right and then
unauthorized request but will do here if
the request is authenticated but or not
authorized then we will return for
region from here so if HTTP context dot
current dot user that identity dot is
authenticated so what I am sick is not
authenticated it should be that one
otherwise
we will override the action wheel over
at the response it should be you to be
message status code should be forbidden
okay so it's done
now we need to add wave API controller
where we will add some action so we can
take a check the token authentication is
working fine or not
so for adding wave API controller in our
application go to your solution Explorer
right click on your controllers folder
then go add and then click on controller
from here we will select web api -
controller i'll select empty and then
click on add button here I will provide
my controller name and Mike is its data
controller then click on add water
so you can see our Web API controller is
created now I will add an action here
for getting data from server for
anonymous user first so it should be
allow anonymous
HTTP GET root api's as dieter slash
for all means for all user
return okay
it's just a simple action just I am
returning current date time of the
server and this action should be
accessible for all type of user do not
need to authenticate and authorization
here now I will add one more action here
this action for authenticated user so I
will first write authorized attribute
because this will check if the request
is authorized then this section will
book and if not then it will return for
0 1 so it
silly result
for authorized user II authenticate
you
so dot if identity okay
so what I have done here this action is
for only authorized user if the user is
authorized then this action will return
the authorized version name hello
authorized version name okay so I'm
going to add one more action here or
authorized user only admin user can
execute that action so I'm going to add
authorize with a nose and the show
I'll check from here because I have done
static so admin and user if admin user
is logged in then this admin user can
access this action so it should be admin
today's yourself
so
public Sun result in Kate
to secure to
take two okay
okay so what I have done here in this
section this at this action only allowed
for the admin user and if it is admin
user then it will return hello and it an
admin username and with the rule okay so
we are almost done we need to just run
this application to check everything is
working fine or not okay so let's run
our application actually we need one
more thing you have or taste or
definitely it will get this one four
zero four because we don't have any
default controller added yoga first so
for testing we need to use postman
Google Chrome extension first our Web
API configuration is ready now we will
taste our application with post postman
and then in the next part of this series
we will create a gorgeous project a
client application for consume our web
api services with token-based
authentication so for test our
application in this stage we need to use
postman is a postman is a extension of
Google Chrome which is used as a client
application to taste the request and
response between web service and client
so first of all I need to run our
application or check everything is
working fine or not but it will get 4:04
real either because we do not have the
default controller now and it's looking
for home controller so what I will do I
will download postman acts extension
from Google Chrome
so you can download from Google Web
Store Chrome Web Store go to there just
click on active Chrome button so it will
add
take a little time because it is
downloading now
you can see here it's added now click on
that so pain okay so first of all what
we will do we will try to access our
action which is for all type of user for
anonymous user before login let's go
back to our equation this is the root
for exes anonymous major action so we
need to waste you know sorry before this
we need to add our vacation URL so this
is our application URL
then it's a gate method click st. yes
you can see here we get response from
server the server time is this one okay
because this is because of this is for
anonymous user but if we try to access
this action now for authenticate user
then it will show a message
authorization has been denied and you
can see here the status code is for 0 1
are not authorized and in case if we
want to access this method so we should
get 4 0 3 so it also returning for 0 1
on unauthorized it let us check once
what we have done mistake you can see
here it is also returning for 0 1
because the request is not authorized
and authenticated now ok so let us try
to login to get the authorization token
and for this we need to go yoga sorry
this is our URL forget the token so what
I will do I'll just remove this one this
should be our post action and if if we
send here then we will get error message
because we need to pass username
password and contact so from here what I
will do I will pass username first I
will log in as a user so we can check
everything is fine or not so this is
user a user type user user and password
is all
user so let's check with that one user
password user and also I need to pass
one more parameter here grant eyes it
should be password so now if I click on
send button you can see here I get
access token token type and expiry in so
now if I want to execute the method just
copy here the access token we need to
pass this access token for access
restricted resources from server so with
this token now we can access this method
the for authenticate because it is for
any authorized user and we cannot access
this one for admin user because I have
generated this token for the user type
user so let's check it's working on the
same way or not so now if I try to
access this one authorized if I send
them it will get we will get this
message because of we have not added the
authorized parameter so for authorized
parameter we need to
first we need to write Varia then we
have to paste this token here now if I
try to send this button
sorry it should be authenticated for
authorized user I will get 4:03 because
it's not the admin user so this action
cannot be accessible with this token
because this is only for the admin type
of user that's the reason I am getting
4:03 forbidden
that means I'm authentic ated but it's
not authorized to admin user so if I try
to access this just copy this one first
and then I try to access the
authenticate user means this action
which is allowed for any logged in user
with that I do the authorize then I will
get response so it's showing hello
Serratia which means this user so it
this for that this user user type user
we can access this method because this
is allowed for all authorized user and
now if we want to access this method so
we need to first log in as an admin user
and we need to get back the token from
server and then we need to access this
method with with the token getting from
the server so what we will do I will do
again I will generate token but this
time with the admin user and click on
send button you can see I am getting one
more token and this token is for admin
role user now if I try to access the
authorized method
this one this authorized method with
this token I've just got failure and
then token now if I click here then I
will get this
hello Saurabh model and role is admin
means this is now working fine
let's check yes you can see here the
breakpoint so this method is now working
because I have logged in as admin user
so everything is working fine now in the
next project sorry
in the next part of this series we will
see how we can use this token-based
authentication in our angularjs
application ok thank you for watching
don't forget to Like comment and
subscribe thank you